

Systems Architect, Software Developer

Centurion, Gauteng, South Africa • phillip.kruger@phillip-kruger.com

phillip-kruger.com github.phillip-kruger.com

Summary

Accomplished Software developer and architect offering experience in creating systems in various industries, ranging from banking, insurance, rewards programs, retail. Extensive experience in full stack development, active in all parts of the SDLC. From conceptualizing to running in production.

Passion for clean code and evolutionary architecture. Loves Java, Linux and Open source.

Professional Experience

Systems Architect

MMI Holdings. Multiply

Multiply is a Wellness and Rewards program that encourage clients to live healthier and reach their financial goals.

I am the Systems Architect and I'm responsible for the overall Architecture of the Systems and the Technical implementation and quality of the systems and teams.

I have a hands-on approach and believe in Clean Code Principles and Evolutionary Architecture.

Our systems range from AS400, Java EE, Javascript etc.

We do a lot of integration to and from Partners and other Product Houses in MMI.

Software consultant

Jul 2014 - Jan 2015

Standard Bank

Key Responsibilities:

- Software POC, design and implementation of Multi-channel service API for Internet banking, Mobile Apps, ATM and other channels
- · Consuming and producing SOAP and REST services
- Continues deployment Automation of infrastructure deployment and configuration
- Part of the Architectural Forum

Technologies used:

Maven, Nexus, Eclipse, Linux, Java (EE & SE), Wildfly, Websphere Application Server 8.5, DB2, Websphere MQ, Spring

IT Director, Enterprise Architect, Software developer

Jun 2008 - Jul 2014

Thumbtribe Mobile Solutions

Key Responsibilities:

- Expert in mobile web technologies.
- Mobile billing, USSD, Feature phone mobile web, smart phone HTML 5
- · Main developer and system analyst.
- Responsible for conducting, leading and coordinating software development activities throughout the project, including key design decisions for the technology, structure and configuration of the system.

Education

Jan 2015 - Current B.Sc (Hons) Computer Science

2001 - 2003

University of Johannesburg

Honors degree in Computer Science, focusing on Security, Web programming, Robotics and AI.

B.Sc Information Technology

1998 - 2000

University of Johannesburg

Major in Computer Science and Informatics.

Other courses **Solms Training**

2000 - 2006

Programming in Java, Advanced Java. XML, Object-Oriented Analysis and Design using UML, Enterprise Java Beans, Patterns, Architecture

Conferences attended

- 2007 Oracle Open World, San Francisco
- 2011 JavaOne, San Francisco
- 2011 Mobile World Congress, Barcelona
- 2015 JavaOne, San Francisco
- 2016 IBM Interconnect, Las Vegas

My Professional Skills

I am an accomplished Software developer and architect offering experience in creating systems in various industries, ranging from banking, insurance, rewards programs, retail and mobile. I have extensive experience in full stack development, and prefer to be active in all parts of the SDLC. From conceptualizing to running in production.

I have a passion for clean code and evolutionary architecture. I love Java, Linux and Open source.

Activities

Squash – Northern league, Gauteng league and Dolphin coast league. I am also Club captain of my local squash club where I maintaining the club website.

- · Monitor Team performance and activity.
- Serve clients, identify their needs and provide feedback on the success of projects.
- Performance Review and management of development of the Team members
- Enforce best practice and environment standards.
- Product definition, design and development of Thumbprint (http://thumbtribe.mobi/info)
- Cloud platform that allows anyone with an internet capable device to build sites (mobile or web) without actually having to "code"
- Hosting of the above mentioned site is also taken care of with the

cloud service.

- The platform has numerous widgets you can use to build your site.
- The platform ensures that the mobi site you built will work on 6500+

devices (everything from a Motorolla V3 to an iPhone)

- Example site built with platform:

http://www.thumbtribe.co.za/

Technologies used: Ant, Gradle, Eclipse, Linux, Java (JEE, JSE), Glassfish, MySQL, openRDF, Lucene Search, Ehcache, Apache Pluto, Spring Web, Apache Velocity, Netbiscuits (BiscuitML), Jquery, Foundation

Enterprise Architect

Aug 2006 - May 2008

Infoware

Key Responsibilities:

• Defining and implementing a new Architecture for Tranquility (Financial

system for the sugar industry) as well as strategies to achieve these goals.

Technologies used: Java, J2EE, JEE, SOA, UML, SOAP Webservices, XML, XSL,

XSD, FTP, Junit, JSF, Linux, MySQL

Software Developer, Technical Team May 2005 - Jul 2006 Lead, Architect

Dariel Solutions

Key Responsibilities:

• Discovery Life (www.discovery.co.za) — Contract work through Dariel

Solutions

- Design and development of the following projects:
- Domain and Policy Administration
- Discovery Life Integration Layer to the Discovery World Systems.
- Discovery Life Retirement Optimizer product
- Discovery Life Claims System
- ${\:\raisebox{3.5pt}{\text{\circle*{1.5}}}}$ Software Audits I was responsible for a two week audit of the South African Post Office Leave Application System

Technologies used: Java EE, Oracle, BEA Weblogic, Eclipse IDE, XML, XSL, Apache FOP, JAXB, UML, SAX, FTP (Apache net project), Flux (Batch Scheduler), Oracle Workflow, Ant, Extreme Programming.

Java Developer

Feb 2001 - Apr 2005

Standard Bank

Key Responsibilities:

- Develop client program to assist International Banking clients with online banking
- Develop web-based inquiry system, providing real-time balances, statements etc. on ZAR accounts held by global institutions.

Skills

Java & Java EE

I have been writing Java since the beginning of Java and still loving it! I stay up to date with the Language and specifications. I have extensive experience in Enterprise Java, including JAX-RS, JAX-WS, CDI, JAXB, JAXP, XML, JSON-P, JSON, JPA, JDBC, EJB, JTA, JCA, JMS, JSF, JSP, Servlets, WebSockets, Bean Validation, Portlets, Spring, Swagger, Lombok and much more

Linux

I have been running Linux on my Personal PC since 1999, starting with Mandrake and then basically went through many distributions including Red Hat, OpenSUSE, Debian, PCLinuxOS. I then discovered Gentoo Linux, and went from a basic Desktop user to being comfortable with building my own OS on my PC. I also used Ubuntu and Mint. For the past few years I have been using Arch Linux and loving it. I am comfortable running and managing Linux servers and Docker containers.

Tools

I have been using many tools through the years. Currently these are some of my favorites: GIT, Gogs, Jenkins, Nexus, SonarQube, Maven, Ansible, Netbeans, Docker

Infrastructure

I enjoy setting up and automating the environments that my systems need to run. MySQL, PostgreSQL, DB2, OpenRDF, Elasticsearch, Wildfly, GlassFish and Payara, TomEE, WAS Liberty, Pluto and more

Communication

I enjoy talking and debating about technical concerns. I blog about technical topics and session feedback from conferences. I also enjoy presenting technical topics in forums. I am comfortable running technical meetings and finding solutions around a white board.

see http://www.phillip-kruger.com/

Other

I have knowledge of many other languages, frameworks and libraries. I believe in using the right tool for the job and can learn a new specification, language or framework quickly and easily. Some of these include HTML5, CSS3, Sass & Less, JavaScript, Semantic UI, Bootstrap, Foundation, PHP, SVG, XSLT, SQL, RDF, SPARQL, Webjars, OPML, ATOM and RSS and more.

Myers-Briggs psychological type

INTJ (introversion, intuition, thinking, judgment)

Strengths

Strategic * Analytical * Achiever * Deliberative * Relator

Personal details

Born: 3 July 1978

Nationality: South African

- Design and develop Sweeping Facility (internal program that Standard Bank uses to move all money from one account to another for a predefined balance at certain times)
- Design and develop a new Electronic Software Distribution, replacing the old ESD on CORBA.
- Redefining and rebuilding the build process for J2EE Projects and Swing clients.
- Design and develop Card Payment Solution (system assists with settlement between buyer and supplier and integrates with ERP system of buyer)

Technologies used: Java Swing, Java Applets, CORBA (on communication to the mid-tier), JBuilder, Solaris, Oracle, RMI (on communication to the mid-tier- BEA WebLogic J2EE Server), HTTP/S CRC, Apache Web Server, Apache Ant (Scripts and Ant task development), J2SDK, xDoclet, JSP and Servlets, PVCS, JBoss, Tomcat, XML, XSL/T, SAP, Business Connector, SOAP (JAX-RPC), JAXP (Java API for XML Processing), JAXB (Java API for XML Binding), JAAS (Security), EJB (Session Beans, Enterprise CMP Beans and CMR), MySQL, Oracle

Software

Some open source libraries and examples I create and maintain in my free time:

Apiee - Swagger on Java EE

Stompee - Websockets log file on Java EE

Klokee - Message input on Java EE

see: https://github.com/phillip-kruger

Published articles

Your own Swagger UI on Liberty Monkey methodology Google might be wrong

Core Competencies

- Software Development
- System Design
- System Architecture
- Enterprise Architecture
- Business Design
- Business Architecture
- Technical Writing
- Technical Presentation

- Communication
- Team Leadership
- Research & Analysis
- Process Improvements